<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>On Guessing Well</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on On Guessing Well</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Oddities of the Principle of Indifference</title>
      <link>/post/oddities-of-the-principle-of-indifference/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/oddities-of-the-principle-of-indifference/</guid>
      <description> Definition of the Principle of Indifference  Principle of Indifference on Countably Infinite Sets  Principle of Indifference on Uncountably Infinite Sets  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A First Attempt w/ Central Tendency</title>
      <link>/post/a-first_attempt-with-central-tendency/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-first_attempt-with-central-tendency/</guid>
      <description>The purpose of this blog is to explore how we can reason about what we know to make guesses about what we don’t. We are going to “dip our toes” into this subject by exploring one of the most commonly experienced concepts in probability theory and statistics: measures of central tendency. Specifically, we are going to revisit the common definitions of measures such as the mean, median, and mode; and attempt to build a stronger intuition of what they are and why they are useful in our goal of making better guesses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About This Blog</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Greetings fellow humanoids,
My name is David W.C. Telson and this blog is all about decision making under uncertainty. We will be exploring all sorts of topics from the realms of probability theory, decision theory, statistics, machine learning, and the philosophy of science.
At present I am a Data Scientist working for the Federal Emergency Management Agency in Washington, DC. Most of the problems I work on involve leveraging machine learning and statistics to support decisions about the Agency&amp;rsquo;s incident workforce and field operations.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>